Hi, everyone.
Welcome to the DevSecOps
2026 conference and
thank you for joining
my session on cell-based
isolation for multi-tenant
platforms on Kubernetes.
I'm Lahiru De Silva,
and currently working as
an associate technical
lead at WSO2 based in
Colombo, Sri Lanka.
And I'm also a maintainer
of the CNCF project
OpenWhisk, which is an open
source internal developer
platform on Kubernetes.
And I'll use OpenWhisk as a
reference architecture for the
cell-based isolation concept
that we are going to talk
in the next thirty minutes.
I'll start the session with
multi-tenancy in Kubernetes
because the word multi-tenancy
means different things to
different people and I want us
to be on the same page before
we go to the main topic.
Who is a tenant in Kubernetes?
Different organization
build different use
cases and different
applications on Kubernetes.
For example some organizations
build their internal
systems on Kubernetes and
some organization build
a SaaS product for their
customers on Kubernetes.
The there's no any single
definition for the word
multi-tenancy or there's
no any single definition
for the word tenant.
It depends on the business
use cases how your
solution is architectured
and how your solution
is built on Kubernetes.
And also it even depends
on the types of users
in your applications.
For example in this
diagram we can see multiple
flavors of multi-tenancy.
On the left-hand side
we have a soft form of
multi-tenancy where basically
the internal teams of an
organization are your tenants.
And the trust between
those tenancies implicit
and also the boundaries
enforced by convention.
That means people agree not
to cross the boundary and if
someone crosses the boundary
you basically go and have
a conversation with them.
And in the middle we have
a form of multi-tenancy
where different business
units or different business
partners of a organization
are treated as tenants.
Compared to the initial case
where multiple teams are
considered as tenants in this
scenario there are contractual
boundaries and in certain
cases there are separate
budgets and in certain cases
there are various security
and compliance requirements.
So the boundaries start
to carry some weight.
On the right, the tenants
are external consumers.
For example, consider consider
users of a SaaS product.
Tenants are
mutually untrusted.
That means one tenant
reaching another tenant's
data is not considered
as a, a simple accident.
It often ends in disaster.
It can end the contract
that you have with the
customer, or in in the
worst case, it can even
end up in a legal lawsuit.
So we can clearly see
why there's no any single
definition for a tenant,
because these use cases
involve different level
of isolation different
levels of trust, and
different levels of risk.
So now let's talk
about tenant isolation.
Kubernetes doesn't provide
any tenant isolation by
default, but it gives you
user set of APIs to build
that isolation for yourself.
So now let's look what
those APIs are and how
to build that isolation.
So here we need to
consider control plane
isolation and data plane
isolation separately.
Control plane isolation
is control plane isolation
is about who can access
different API object.
For example in control
plane isolation, we have
namespaces role-based access
control, and resource quotas.
Namespaces are used to
basically group resources,
and then role-based access
control is used to restrict f-
restrict access to resources.
And then resource quota
are basically used to
restrict different usage,
different resource usages
to your applications.
Data plane isolation is about
what a running application
is allowed to do at runtime.
This include things
like storage isolation,
network isolation, and
sandboxing containers with
things like gVisan Kata
Containers, and also the
node isolation with different
taints and tolerations,
and also maintaining
different dedicated node
pools for certain tenants
So now let's talk why network
isolation is difficult.
If you look at the diagram
on the left side, on the
left-hand side you can
see there are things like
namespaces, access control
node isolation, sandboxing.
Typically, all these things
are usually configured
by a platform team, and
then for the developer,
you will only get a set
of configuration options.
So that means for example,
for namespaces, a platform
team will usually configure
a single namespace per
tenant, or in advanced use
cases, it can be multiple
namespaces for a tenant.
And when it comes to the
access control, usually
a platform engineer team
will basically set up some
different user types, and the
developers or the users will
inherit those user types based
on the provided permissions.
For node isolation, it's
fairly straightforward,
so you will either have
a shared node pool, or
you will have a dedicated
node pool per tenant.
And when it comes to the
container sandboxing,
typically a single
organization will have a
single technology, like either
Kata Containers or gVisor,
based on their use cases.
And if they have really
advanced use cases, they
may… they may have
requirement to use different
types of container sandboxing.
And for resource quotas,
it's usually typically
a single number.
A platform engineer team will
maintain a set of resource
quotas depending on the
use cases and depending on
the nature of applications.
And compared to that,
now let's see why network
isolation is difficult to
model and difficult to think.
When we talk about network
isolation, it's basically the
developer or the development
team who will decide what
kind of services or what
kind of other applications
that your application
will communicate with.
For example like in certain
cases, your application
may have a requirement
to communicate to some
other application in the
same tenant, which lives
in a separate namespace.
And in certain cases, you have
requirement to calls other
external SaaS APIs, and then
basically call other services
in the public internet And
also in certain cases you
have a requirement to call
a shared platform service.
All these network
configurations and all these
communication configuration
is basically a property of
your application, and it's
for the platform engineers,
it's difficult to predefine or
template these requirements.
So the application
development team will
dictate the requirements.
As a platform engineer team
you will have to basically
be flexible and then you will
have to manage these various
networking requirements
case by case, depending on
the application use cases.
Due to these reasons overall
when we compare network
isolation with other isolation
strategies like namespaces,
it is pretty difficult
to have a unified model
How do organizations
actually solve this problem?
The usual answer is network
micro-segmentation, which
means breaking the cluster
into small segments and
then controlling the
traffic between them.
Let's how- let's look how
that works in Kubernetes
Yeah, so this is the
standard answer, and it's
fairly straightforward.
In the top diagram, you can
see like there are two tenants
and they live in two different
namespaces, and there are no
any network policies in place.
So the API component in the
tenant A can freely talk
to a database in tenant B.
And compared to that in
the bottom diagram, you
can see there's a network
policy and API component
in the API component in
the tenant A, it cannot
directly call the database
in the tenant B. This is
blocked by a network policy.
So if your use cases are
fairly straightforward
like this, let's say if you
can model your tenant in
a single namespace with a
single network policy and
only a handful of services,
then having a single
network policy is generally
enough for your use case.
The interesting question
is what happens when
they don't stay this way?
So to understand how this
simple model gets complex and
when the applications evolve
let's consider the scenarios.
Let's consider in the first
year like you have a one
tenant, one namespace,
and three services.
Like you have three services
like web, API, and DB.
All these applications live
in a single namespace, and
you can have a single network
policy to isolate this tenant
from the other tenants.
So the setup is fairly
straightforward, one namespace
and one network policy.
And here, the most
important thing is your
tenancy boundaries,
basically the namespace
and the network policy.
You can directly define
what your tenancy boundaries
And now in the second
year, let's say your
application has evolved,
and then you distribute your
application among between
like four namespaces.
And like it usually happen for
various good reasons, like you
want to have more isolation
in your applications and then
basically you want to have
fine level access controls.
And even in some cases,
some organization some
organizations have decided
to adopt microservices
and you want to have a
separate namespace per team.
For those reasons,
you basically deploy
your applications in
multiple namespaces.
Now now when we look at this
from a network perspective,
you can see now the
networking configuration is
complicated when we compare
with the previous scenario.
Now you have inter-namespaces
or cross-tenant communication
that you need to control
with network policies.
And also in the same
time, you need to define
the tenancy boundary.
So if we compare it with
the previous scenario,
in the previous scenario,
we can directly say
your tenancy boundary
is basically a namespace
and a network policy.
But in this scenario we can't
directly say what our tenancy
boundary is because it's a
combination of namespaces,
and it's a combination
of network policies.
And each of these namespaces
will have different network
policies based on the
application requirement.
So now by just looking
at a diagram, it's pretty
difficult to picture
the tenancy boundary
Now let's say you are
basically a platform
engineer of a platform
team who manage these
multi-tenancy environments.
In that case, you
have ten, 15, or even
hundreds of tenants.
So if we look at the holistic
view, now you can see you have
tenants with very complicated
network configurations and
those configurations will get
multiplied by your factor.
If you have 20 tenants,
then those networking
rules will get multiplied
will get multiplied by 20.
And in certain cases, like
some tenants may have very
special network rules which
are like based, which are
basically defined based on
their networking requirements.
So as a platform engineer
or as a platform team,
it's pretty difficult
for you to picture
everything in your head.
And then it's pretty
difficult to manage these
networking configurations
as the applications evolve.
What's actually broken here?
So if we look at the whole
networking configuration
that we discussed, we can see
there are no any defaults.
That means deny something
is something that you have
to remember and something
that you have to write.
So if you forget the
default policy or the
default rule, then the, the
tenant is basically open
to all the other tenants
And most importantly
there's no identity.
So Kubernetes network
policies usually work
at the network layer.
That means you basically
enforce different network
policies based on labels,
IPs, pod labels, and
various Kubernetes labels.
So here reachability is not
authentication natively we
don't have any identity in the
Kubernetes network policies.
And this model
doesn't compose.
That means if you have more
tenants then your networking
configuration will get
multiplied by a factor.
There are a lot of network
policies that you will have
to manage, and there's a
high chance that you will
make a mistake which get
reflected in one of your
tenant's applications.
And most importantly the
networking configuration
cannot be reviewed.
That means let's say you
apply network policies
and you basically have a
set of network policies.
Like if if a application sees
a timeout, you can't directly
point the network policy
which caused the timeout
because like you have bunch
of network policies, and you
will have to go, you will
have to go through them, and
you will have to evaluate
why this timeout occurred.
So it's pretty difficult
to review the network
configuration as the
complexity grows.
When we put all these
factors together, we
can see the root cause.
So we are trying to
enforce a boundary where
we never modeled it.
The tenant exists in
the documentation in
the billing system, but
there's no any proper
representation of the tenant
in the Kubernetes cluster.
So the fix is not to
have a better rule.
So the fix is to give
a boundary give the
tenancy boundary a name,
a shape, and a default
Which brings me to
serverless architecture
coming to the cell-based
architecture, it's an
approach that structure
an entire system with
distributed, independent,
and self-contained
units called cells.
Cell-based architecture was
co-authored by our current
CTO, Asanka Abayasinghe,
and our founding CTO, Paul
Freemont, as a part of WSO2
reference architecture back in
two thousand eighteen summer.
So here self-contained means
component can freely talk with
each other inside the cell.
And one way means the
concept of cell gateway,
where there's a cell
gateway and the…
if you want to communicate
with some component inside
the cell you have to
go through the gateway.
And here bounded bounded
context means a cell will
always have one functional
domain owned by a single
team, and the team will take
care of running the cell
and basically managing it.
So if you are familiar
with domain-driven design,
this is the same idea.
And cells are versioned
and immutable.
That means once you build and
deploy your cell, you will
have to replace it as a unit.
You can't patch it.
For our session today
the most important points
are the first two points.
That means the cell is a
self-contained entity, and
there's a cell gateway.
So if you want to talk to
some components inside the
cell, you will have to go
through the cell gateway.
So that's a completely
different completely
different philosophy from
what we discussed before.
Because because in the
previous model we discussed,
there are no defaults.
There are no any like any
model that governs the
networking configurations.
So here, this is a
pretty solid model that
basically describes how
your applications are
restricted using this
domain-driven design.
Here's how cell
connectivity works.
There are four traffic
directions, and let's have
a look on each of them.
Northbound ingress means
basically the public traffic
that are coming to your
application from the internet.
And southbound egress means
basically traffic that
is leaving from your cell
to the external world.
And westbound ingress
means basically the ingress
traffic that is coming
from other cells of your
tenant to your cell.
And eastbound egress means
basically the egress traffic
that is leaving your cell
and going to the other
cells in your organization.
And inside the cell,
components can talk freely.
There's no any network
policies or any gateway and
components are basically free
to talk with each other now
you can see by just looking
at the diagram, the whole
networking configuration
for a tenant, and you
can basically visualize
and you can model it.
Let's see a comparison
between maintaining
network rules and modeling
this problem as a cell.
If we look at the scalability,
now if you have rules,
then you will always have
a multiplication factor.
So when the number of tenants
grow, you will have a lot of
network rules to maintain,
and it's pretty difficult to
picture the whole networking
configuration in your head.
If you have a cell
the scalability is
always additive.
That means if you have a
tenant, then you basically
go ahead and add a new cell.
And regarding the default,
so if you have rules,
then you will have to
remember the default.
That means either you
will have to template
it or you will have to
remember it somehow.
And, If you consider the
cell architecture, then
there's always a default
network configuration, and
it is already taken care of.
And next if you want to
answer the question, what
can this application or what
can this workload reach?
If you have typical network
rules, then you will have
to run experiment, and then
only you can answer what
this application or what
this workload is allowed
to communicate with.
But if you have a cell,
then by just looking at
the cell configuration, you
can answer that question.
And when we take a bound--
when we consider the boundary,
if you have typical network
rules, then the, like there
is no any concrete boundary
and the boundary will depend
on the type of networking
rules that you will have.
But in contrast with that,
in the cell architecture, the
boundaries are well-defined
object, where like you
can exactly say what
is the boundary and how
the boundary is modeled.
So now we talk about
cell-based architecture
as a concept.
Now let's see how we have
implemented cell-based
architecture in open career.
Quick note on open career.
Open career is a modular
open source developer
platform on Kubernetes.
It was developed by WSO2
and donated to CNCF as a
CNCF sandbox project in
January twenty twenty-six.
It provides high
level platform and
developer abstractions.
If you look at the diagram,
you get the core idea.
Platform teams will
build golden paths and
platform standards.
So we usually call that
shift down moving the
complexity into the platform
layer rather than pushing
it to the developers.
And then the software
teams they can ship
applications through
self-service workflows.
And both sides are designed
to be used by humans
and AI agents through
the same interfaces
and same guardrails.
So I'm not going to do a…
like I'm not going to explain
the whole platform today.
I'm just showing it because
cells are like a very
first class concept in
open career, and I want
to use it as a reference
architecture and see how
this cell-based architecture
lands in practice.
So very briefly, I will go
through the architecture.
So open career has, has a
multi-plane architecture
where we have like set of
planes for different purposes.
Basically, we have divided
open career into multi-plane
architecture to cater various
use cases like separation
of concerns, and then you
can run different planes in
different infrastructure,
and then you can scale
the plane separately.
So if you consider the
control plane, it's like
the brain of OpenCoro.
It holds the API server,
the controllers, and it
basically maintain the
whole state of the system.
And data plane is the plane
where your applications
actually run with
regard to this session.
So that's where
the cells live.
And workflow plane is the
place where your applications
are being built and basically
like you can build your
applications in the workflow
plane, and then you can
push your application to
some container registry.
Observability plane
basically collects logs,
metrics, and traces, and
it basically holds the
telemetry data of the system.
And on the left, we can
see the experience plane.
So that's basically contains
the backstage portal OpenCoro
CLI and VS Code plugin,
and basically a set of M-
MCP servers for AI agents
which basically relies
on the same interfaces as
the humans So now let's
discuss how how the cell is
represented in OpenCorio.
On the left side, you can
see the control pane, and
in OpenCorio, there's a
concept called projects.
Basically create projects,
and then inside the
project you can create
components which are
basically your applications.
When you create a project
in OpenCorio it will
basically create some
set of cells in the data
plane based on the number
of environments you have.
So OpenCorio also has
this environment concept
where you can define
multiple environments.
So now let's say in the
diagram, like you basically
have two tenants, and
two tenants and basically
in the tenant Acme,
you have two projects.
And in the tenant
Example Inc., you
have a single project.
Now, for this scenario, let's
say like there are three
environments in OpenCorio.
So in that case, like for
a single project, three
cells will be generated.
Since we have three
projects here, nine
cells will be generated.
So the key point here
is like nobody will
write a network policy.
As developers, you basically
go ahead and basically
create some projects.
And from the OpenCorio
platform layer, it
will bootstrap all the
network policies, and
it will take care of all
the tenant isolation.
It will basically deploy a
cell which define the tenant
isolation boundary, and
it will be implement as a,
like the, the cell will be
implemented as a standard
Kubernetes net-network policy,
or it will be a Cilium network
policy if Cilium is installed.
So now let's discuss
how developers interact
with the cells.
In OpenCorio, we have a
concept called endpoints,
where the developers can
basically declare their intent
to expose their applications
to different boundaries like
public internet intranet.
So based on the requirements,
the developers will
basically declare their
intent as a endpoint.
In OpenCorio, there are
four types of endpoints.
Project level endpoints,
namespace endpoints
internal endpoints,
and external endpoints.
If you look at the diagram
in the cell CRM, you can see
there are two components.
And in the component
API, there's a, a
project level endpoint.
The other components inside
the cell CRM project can
consume this endpoint
through the project level
endpoint And next we have
namespace-level endpoints.
Here in the diagram the
sale billing can access
any any component inside
the sales CRM if those
components are exposed as
namespace-level endpoints.
That means basically in
the control pane we have
we have this concept
called namespaces.
Inside the namespace, you can
create multiple projects, and
inside the project you can
create multiple components.
So all these component
can communicate with
each other using the
namespace-level endpoints.
And then next we have
internal endpoints.
So in internal endpoints,
you can as a developer, you
can basically deploy your
API to a internal gateway,
where that API can be
consumed by, that API can be
consumed by other consumers
in your organization.
So this is more relevant
for scenarios where
your application where
your organization
has a business unit.
For example let's say you you
basically build some solution
and then you deploy your
API to some internal gateway
and some other business
unit will consume that API
through the internal gateway
which basically lives in a
separate tenant namespace.
And then finally, we have
the public endpoints.
If you have application
where that you need
to expose it to public
internet, you can basically
define a public endpoint.
And the most important
thing here is that as a
developer, you did not pro…
work with any low-level
infrastructure, things
like gateways, listeners.
Like you didn't provide any
certificate or hostnames.
As a developer, you just
declared your intent and
OpenCorp as a platform
layer, it take it basically
translate your intent to
some low-level configuration
which are applied to the
Kubernetes clusters So
now let's talk about cell
observability in OpenCorio.
So previously we talked about
how as a developer you can
deploy some applications
to OpenCorio cell, and then
expose it using endpoints.
Now as a developer or as
even a platform engineer,
you have a requirement
to have observability or
basically to see what's
happening inside the cell.
Even though you have a
boundary, and if you can't
see anything hap… that
is happening inside the
boundary, then there's no
value of that boundary.
From OpenCorio perspective
OpenCorio has observability
built into the platform
as a first-class thing.
So OpenCorio will capture
the logs, metrics, and
traces of your applications.
And also additionally
if Cilium is installed,
it will even do advanced
capabilities like layer seven
observability, and also you
can see via logs of your
application in the TCP level.
And most of these things
are collected by the
in a infrastructure
level components we
have in OpenCorio.
And at the collection time,
we basically take all we
basically label all the
observability data with
OpenCorio specific concepts
like namespaces, project,
environments, and components.
So after that you basically
get a unified observability
view in the platform.
So I'm going to basically
do a quick demo on that
in the upcoming session
And then if you talk
about some multi-tenancy
patterns in OpenCoro, so
we can like OpenCoro is
built to be very flexible.
There are a set of
multi-tenancy patterns
that we can discuss.
In OpenCoro, you can have a
data plane per tenant, like
you can have a namespace
per tenant, or even you can
have a project per tenant.
So based on your use
cases, you can have a
different tenancy model.
If you have a data plane
per tenant, then that you
basically have a you can
define a data plane per
tenant, and then you can
use a separate Kubernetes
cluster per tenant.
In that case, you have a very
physical, you have the most
isolation and compared to
that let's say you basically
have a single Kubernetes
cluster, and then you model
your tenants as namespaces.
So in that case your tenants
are basically sharing a
single Kubernetes cluster.
Compared to the pattern one
this has less isolation,
but when it comes to the
infrastructure cost and also
the cost of managing the
infrastructure all those
things should be considered.
And if we consider the
pattern three, where you have
a project per tenant, then
this basically shares the
same data plane, which means
you have a single Kubernetes
cluster for your tenants.
And also this shares
the namespace as well.
So basically so basically you
will have multiple tenants
in a single namespace.
So this is more suitable
for scenarios like you have
subteams inside a team, so the
team will be a namespace and
the project will be a subteam
So now I will do a OpenCoro
product walkthrough where
we can see the concept
that we discussed so far.
And then we can see how we
have implemented the cell
architecture in OpenCoro as
a reference implementation.
So now I'm going to log
into OpenCoro platform
as a platform engineer.
I'm going to use the
default credentials
And once you log into this
OpenCoro platform, you
can-- you get this homepage.
So from here, you can see
the multi-plane concept
that I explained previously.
There's one cluster data
plane connected to this
OpenCoro control plane.
There's one workflow
plane, and there's one
observability plane.
And if I go to catalog,
you can see the
default project here.
And also from the catalog,
you can see various
OpenCoro abstractions
like projects, components,
APIs, and also platform
resources like environments
and deployment pipelines.
I will go inside the default
project, and you can see
there are two components
that I have deployed.
And as I explained previously
in the session, so in
OpenCoro when you create
a project, OpenCoro will
automatically create a cell.
And based on the Kubernetes
network CNI that you have im--
you basically configured, it
will be a standard Kubernetes
network policy, or it will
be a Cilium network policy.
Inside the project, you can
go inside the cell diagram.
In the cell diagram, you
can see the two components
and the project cell.
Both of these components
are exposed to public
internet via the gateway.
And you can also enable this
run runtime observability,
and then you can basically
filter some timestamp,
and then you can see the
actual observability data.
So here you can see, So
you can see things like
request count, error
percentage, and the latency.
So all the traffic
related information, you
can see it from here.
And also at the project level
we have this log section
where you can see you can see
the logs of your components.
So inside the project, you
can see all the logs of logs
of all the components in
the project, and also traces
and also at the component
level also we have logs.
So at this level, you
can see logs of the
individual components.
And also here you can see
various other observability
data like Kubernetes events
and also the metrics.
From here, you can see you
can see the resource CPU
usage and also the memory
usage and things like network
latency and throughput.
Also in the component
level there's a section
called Wire Logs.
So from here you can from
here you can start capturing
the wire logs and like you
basically need to send some
request, and then you can
see, You can basically see
that TCP level information
So I'm going to
invoke that endpoint
So from here you can
see the wire logs.
From here you can see
the TCP level SYN and
ACK and also from here
you can see the layer
seven observability data.
And you can click on
these and then you can see
various information like
the network protocol and the
source IP, destination IP.
So also the layer seven
information, like the URL,
the method, and the request.
From here, you can see
the request headers.
And you can also get
a raw payload of the,
this observability data.
And that bring us to
the end of the talk.
And I hope this gave you a
useful perspective on the
topic and some practical
ideas that you can take away
and apply in your own work.
Thank you all for taking
time to join me today,
and I really appreciate
your time and attention.
If you have any questions,
thoughts or experience that
you'd like to share, I'd
be happy to discuss it.
Thank you.